<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copie of a letter from His Highnesse Prince Charles, to the speaker of the House of Peeres. Expressing his contentment concerning the votes of the House of Peeres, for a personal treaty with his royall father. With his desires concerning the same.</title>
            <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79173</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.12[100]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869755</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869755</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162891</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79173)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162891)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f12[100])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copie of a letter from His Highnesse Prince Charles, to the speaker of the House of Peeres. Expressing his contentment concerning the votes of the House of Peeres, for a personal treaty with his royall father. With his desires concerning the same.</title>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Given under our Hand and Seale from aboard the Fleet in the Downes, the 5. day of August, in the 24. yeere of the Raigne of the King our Royall Father.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Treaties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:162891:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Copie of a Letter from His Highneſſe Prince <hi>CHARLES,</hi> To the Speaker of the Houſe of Peeres.</head>
            <head type="sub">Expreſſing his contentment concerning the Votes of the Houſe of Peeres, for a Perſonall Treaty with His Royall Father. With His deſires concerning the ſame.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>Charles P.</signed>
            </opener>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight truſty and right well beloved Couſin, we greet you well.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding with great contentment that the two Houſes of Parliament have reſolved upon a Perſonall Treaty with His Majeſty, (one of the particulars preſſed by us in our Declaration of the 29. of <hi>July</hi> laſt, as moſt conducing to the ſettlement of a bleſſed Peace) We have thought fit to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with our ſenſe &amp; deſires concerning the ſame, to the end that they may be communicated by you to the Houſe of Peers from us. Firſt, we propoſe, That the Treaty be appointed to be in ſuch place, and in ſuch manner, as may beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with the Honour, Freedome, and Safety of His Majeſty, whereby the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be made, may not be blemiſhed with any face of reſtraint. Secondly, That the Treaty may be betwixt His Majeſty and His two Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo as the matters in difference may equally fall under the conſideration of all perſons concerned therein. Thirdly, that during the ſaid Treaty, there be a generall Ceſſation of Armes, to the end that the affections of the people, though engaged in ſeverall parties, may thereby be prepared to meet in amity and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindneſſe, and that no intervening accidents or ſucceſſes may diſturb the proceedings in this Treaty. Laſtly, That an orderly moderate ſubſiſtence du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Treaty may be agreed upon for all Armies and Forces now on foot, and particularly for the Scotiſh Army, in ſuch manner as may be with the leaſt preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on the Northerne Counties. And if the two Houſes ſhall think fit to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto the effect of what we now propound, as proper to render this Treaty ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall, we ſhall with great joy and alacrity interpoſe our mediation to the King our Father for the obtaining of all ſuch Conceſsions and Acts of Grace, as by the bleſsing of God may moſt conduce to a firm and laſting Peace, and the happineſſe of His Majeſty and all His People. We farther deſire you to propound to the Houſe of Peeres, That ſome equall courſe may be ſpeedily ſetled for the ſupport of Us and the Navy with us, whereby we may be enabled to protect the Trade of the Kingdome, and may forthwith diſcharge all Ships and Merchandizes now ſtaid by Vs.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under our Hand and Seale from aboard the Fleet in the Downes, <date>the 5. day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the 24. yeere of the Raigne of the King our Royall Father.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>To our Right Truſtly, and Right well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Couſin, the Speaker of the Houſe of Peeres for the time being.</trailer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
